All right, welcome to
module nine, video three.
This one's important
because it is a coding
question on the exam,
and it's a sneaky one.
In the prior video, we used
case expressions in the select
statement, and we also would use
an alias. So we would say, and
as, and then give the column
a name to solve some problems.
In this case, we're gonna use
a case expression and an order
by, and here's how the question
came about. Are you smarter than
a student? We had Conservice at
Focus Friday a few years ago,
And at the last minute, I was
asked to ask Conservist IT people
a SQL question that they might
struggle with. And so I asked
them this. We need a list of
states ordered in ascending order.
Yippee, super simple,
except we want Montana.
Montana is, if you look up the state with
the most pride, Montana is number one.
This year it's tied with Alaska,
but we know Montana is number one.
Montana needs to be at the top
of the list, even though it's
out of order. And you've seen
where you fill out a form and
because you're from a certain
state or most likely from a
certain state, then that state
shows up at the top of the list
so you can easily check it.
And that's what we want here.
Ultimately, we're going to use a case
expression in the order by clause.
And so the Conservis IT professionals
were struggling and then a
student raised their hand and said,
you could just do a case expression in
the order by. So that's what we're
going to do. This will be, again,
a coding question on the exam. so
here we have the states that we're
interested in and so in this case I'm
just going to change this to state
and we know we need an order by and
part of this is going to be order
by state and technically ASC for
ascending order but that will be the
second criteria we need a criteria
in front and as you know you don't
do two order by as you separate it
by comma. So now we need to figure
out where is this case statement
going to be and what's it going to do?
And conceptually, we want,
what do we want to happen?
We want case state. So
we know this is just a
simple case expression, a
type one case expression.
And we know we're dealing with Montana.
So when it's Montana,
then, dash,
let's give it a zero.
And then, because we know
it's ascending order by
default. And then otherwise,
let's give it a one.
Now, we do have to end our case
expression, but we don't end it using
end as, because we're not creating
an alias. We only did that in
select statement when it was going
to create the heading for a new
column. And now I already have
the comma here. We do separate the
first criteria from the second
criteria. Usually we would do that
with, for instance, order by last
name, comma first name in case
there's a tie and then comma by
something else if there's a tie there.
And so let me back this
up and that's it. This is
the code. K-State, when it's
Montana, give it a zero,
otherwise one. So Montana should
be at the top, everybody else
is below it. Otherwise, let's
just do it alphabetized A to Z.
Boom, there it is. Montana's at the
top, and then of course the rest
of them are alphabetized. So
this is the code that you'll need
on the first exam when you solve
a case expression in the order by,
in order to put your favorite
state, hopefully Montana at the
top, or some other topic,
you'll put something at the top.
That's module nine, and we will see
you in a week for module 10. Thank you.